Guide to the Church Women United in Houston Records
University of Houston Libraries
Church Women United in Houston Records
1911-2011
1989-2006
2001-001
Church Women United in Houston
6.00 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Information in the collection includes material on the history of the organization, business and financial records, materials from the three annual celebrations, and programs from area worship services. It also includes yearbooks, photographs, and scrapbooks.
Historical Note:
Church Women United is a national ecumenical organization dedicated to bringing together religious women in order to celebrate and expand their faith, to promote peace and prayer, and to join together as a community to encourage spirituality and advocacy. Church Women United is divided into four levels: national, regional, state, and local. At the national level, the United Council of Church Women was formed in December 1941, when delegates from three inter-denominational women's groups approved a constitution and established an office in New York City. This Council represented women from seventy Protestant denominations. In 1950, the Council became one of twelve interdenominational agencies that comprised the National Council of Churches of Christ in the United States. In 1966, the organization's name was changed to Church Women United in order to encourage the participation of non-Protestant women, such as Roman and Orthodox Catholics.
In 1911, a group of Houston women of different denominations formed the Houston City Federation of Missionary Society; by 1946 the organization was known as the Houston Council of Church Women. The name was changed to Church Women United of Houston in 1966, and to Church Women United in Houston in 1968. At the local level, groups are organized into committees that administer programs and projects; in Houston, the women hold meetings at the many Houston area churches that are members of CWU. Church Women United in Houston participates in worship services at area churches and works with other Houston organizations to promote awareness of a number of issues, including the elderly, women and children, and the environment. Members of the Houston group also participate in the three annual Church Women United celebrations: World Day of Prayer, May Fellowship Day, and World Community Day.
Sources:
Church Women United, Information Handbook and Directory, September 1999 through August 2000, p. 11, located in Box 1, Folder 3.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
Church Women United in Houston
Genre/Form of Material:
Administrative records; Newsletters; Photographs; Programs (documents); Yearbooks
Topical Term:
Christian women -- United States -- Texas -- Houston; Women -- Religious aspects -- Christianity; Women -- Societies and clubs -- Texas -- Houston
Acquisition Information:
Originally acquired from Mabel Cavanagh in 2000. Additional materials were acquired in 2011 as part of a donation by Mabel Cavanagh.
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Related Materials:
For further information on women and religious activity in Houston, please see Brigid's Place Records http://archon.lib.uh.edu/?p=collections/controlcard&id=317
Scope and Contents
The collection arrived at the archives in good order and in general the original order has been maintained. Although primarily concerned with Church Women United in Houston, the collection also contains material from the state and national levels. Information in the collection includes material on the history of the organization, business and financial records, materials from the three annual celebrations, and programs from area worship services. It also includes yearbooks, photographs, and scrapbooks. The collection is divided into eight series: History, Administrative, Activities, Yearbooks, Holly Hall, Community Resource and Development, Photographs, and Ephemera. All of the series are arranged in alphabetical order, except for History, Yearbooks and Ephemera, which are in chronological order.
Detailed List of Contents
- History, 1911-2002
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains a history of the Houston group, as well as brochures and a handbook describing Church Women United at the national level. The series also includes a book, Just Because, the Story of Church Women United in the U.S.A. 1941-1975, by Margaret Shannon, a former executive director of the national organization, published in 1977.
  - Organization History, 1911-1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Organization History, 1960-1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Brochures, 1951-1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Just Because, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Handbook, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Administrative, 1959-2002
  The series consists of the business and financial records of the organization, including reports, minutes, and membership information. The newsletters in this series are those of Church Women United in Houston.
  - Annual/President's Reports, 1959-1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Annual/President's Reports, 1986, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Constitution, By-laws, Standing Rules, 1965-1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1988-2000 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Financial Reports, 1965-1997 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Membership Rosters, 1979-1989 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Membership Rosters, 1989-1992 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Membership Rosters, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Minutes - Board of Managers, 1965-1994 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Minutes - General Assembly, 1965-1994 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Newsletters, 1987-1994 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Nominating Committee, 1989-1992 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Scholarships, 1987-1992, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Certificate of Appreciation Form, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Job Descriptions, 2001-2002 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Membership Forms, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Membership Information, undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Membership Roster, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Press, undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Quotation by Tom Brokaw, undated (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Activities, 1979-2011
  This series contains material concerning the organization's activities at the local, state, and national level and is divided into three sub-series reflecting those levels. The series includes church service programs, newsletters, and brochures. The newsletters in this series are those from the national and state levels of Church Women United.
  - Local
    - Celebrations
      - 1990 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - 1991 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - 1992 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - 1994 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - 1998 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - 1999 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - 2000 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - 2001 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Celebrations Information, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Programs
      - Church World Service, 1989-1992 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Interfaith Workshops, 1965-1989 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Programs, 1987-1993 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Programs, 1994-2001 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Women in Community Service, 1979-1988 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - May Friendship Day, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 14)
      - World Day of Prayer, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 15)
      - World Community Day, November 4, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 16)
      - May Friendship Day, 2006 (Box 6, Folder 17)
      - World Day of Prayer, March 3, 2006 (Box 6, Folder 18)
      - “A Balm in Gilead”, September 5, 2008 (Box 6, Folder 19)
      - World Community Day, November 7, 2008 (Box 6, Folder 20)
      - World Day of Prayer, March 6, 2009 (Box 6, Folder 21)
      - World Day of Prayer, March 5, 2010 (Box 6, Folder 22)
      - World Day of Prayer, March 4, 2011 (Box 6, Folder 23)
      - May Friendship Day, 2011 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - General Assembly Programs
      - Bethel United Church of Christ, February 2, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 25)
      - Bellaire Christian Church, January 10, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 26)
      - The Women’s Home, February 7, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 27)
      - Terrace United Methodist Church, April 4, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 28)
      - Wheeler Avenue Baptist Church, October 3, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 29)
      - Chapelwood United Methodist Church, November 7, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 30)
      - Juan Marcos Presbyterian Church, December 5, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 31)
      - First Congregational Church, February 6, 2004 (Box 6, Folder 32)
      - Pilgrim Congregation United Church of Christ, April 2, 2004 (Box 6, Folder 33)
      - Pines Presbyterian Church, May 7, 2004 (Box 6, Folder 34)
      - St. Luke’s Presbyterian Church, September 3, 2004 (Box 6, Folder 35)
      - St. Luke’s United Methodist Church, October 1, 2004 (Box 6, Folder 36)
      - Bellaire Christian Church, December 3, 2004 (Box 6, Folder 37)
      - First Cumberland Presbyterian Church, January 7, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 38)
      - St. Mary’s United Methodist Church, February 4, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 39)
      - Epworth-Parker United Methodist Church, May 6, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 40)
      - Christ Church Cathedral, September 2, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 41)
      - St. Philip’s United Methodist Church, February 3, 2006 (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - Wheeler Avenue Baptist Church, September 8, 2006 (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - Silver Palace Restaurant, November 3, 2006 (Box 6, Folder 44)
      - El Mesias united Methodist Church, December 1, 2006 (Box 6, Folder 45)
      - Pines Presbyterian Church, February 2, 2007 (Box 6, Folder 46)
      - Unknown, February 1, 2008 (Box 6, Folder 47)
      - Pines Presbyterian Church, December 5, 2008 (Box 6, Folder 48)
      - Holly Hall Retirement Community, December 4, 2009 (Box 6, Folder 49)
      - Terrace United Methodist Church, February 5, 2010 (Box 6, Folder 50)
      - Pines Presbyterian Church, May 7, 2010 (Box 6, Folder 51)
      - Payne Cathedral of Faith, September 10, 2010 (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Newsletters
      - December 2002 (Box 6, Folder 53)
      - January-May, September-December 2003 (Box 6, Folder 54)
      - January-May, September-December 2004 (Box 6, Folder 55)
      - February-May, September-December 2005 (Box 6, Folder 56)
      - January-May, September-November 2006 (Box 6, Folder 57)
      - January-May, September-December 2007 (Box 6, Folder 58)
      - January-May, September, November-December 2008 (Box 6, Folder 59)
      - January-May, September-December 2009 (Box 6, Folder 60)
      - January-May, September-December 2010 (Box 6, Folder 61)
      - January-March, May-June 2011 (Box 6, Folder 62)
  - State
    - Assembly, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Assembly, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Assembly, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1988-1992 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Directory, 1986-1989 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Directory, 1989-1991 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Newsletters, 1988-1998 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - National
    - Brochures, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, 1982-1992 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Ethical Choices Workshop, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Fund for the Fifth Decade, 1981-1984 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Gift Certificates, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Health Care, 1991-1994 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Yearbooks, 1951-2010
  This series contains yearbooks which list the officers, directors, projects, and programs for each year. Within this range of dates, only a few yearbooks are missing: 1955, 1956, and 1995.
  - 1951-1952 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - 1953-1954, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 1958-1960 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - 1962-1964 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - 1965-1967 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - 1968-1970 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - 1990, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - 1993 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - 1994, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - 1997-1998 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - 1999-2000 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - 2001-2002 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - 2003-2004 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - 2005, 2008 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - 2009-2010 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Holly Hall, 1960-1966
  This series contains information related to Holly Hall, a non-profit retirement community in Houston. In 1949, CWU in Houston proposed building a retirement home. By the next year, the project had grown to the extent that CWU in Houston was no longer able to financially sponsor the home, and in 1951 that task was relegated to the Holly Hall Board of Directors. However, Church Women United in Houston continued to act as Holly Hall's spiritual sponsor; CWU in Houston raised over $12,000 in 1951 for the project, and several CWU officers served on the Board of Directors of Holly Hall. Ground was broken and a cornerstone laid in 1951, and the home opened in 1952. For more information, please visit the Holly Hall web site at www.hollyhall.org.
  - Architectural Drawings, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Audit Report, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Audit Report, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - By-laws, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Committee Reports, 1962-1965 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Financial Reports, 1960-1966 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Report on Examination of Accounts, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Community Resource and Development, 1985-1998
  The series contains material of interest to Church Women United on a number of topics. Certain folders in this series contain items on a particular subject from several sources, while other folders contain material from only one organization.
  - Children and Family Services, 1987-1998 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Christian Community Service Center, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Committee, 1986-1995 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Elder Services, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Environmental Issues, 1993-1998 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Greater Houston Women's Foundation, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Houston Metropolitan Ministries, 1981-1991 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Mental Health Organizations, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous, 1988-1998 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - New Directions Club, 1988-1997 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - United Way, 1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Women in Action, 1985-1997 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Photographs, 1981-1988
  This series contains photographs previously held in magnetic albums, but they have been removed for preservation purposes. Some of the individuals have been identified. Folder 13, Miscellaneous, contains photographs which were neither in an album, nor were the individuals identified.
  - CWU Causeway, November 1988 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Community Resource and Development Committee, Fall 1988 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Dallas State Assembly, September 1987 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Leadership Training, May 1987 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - May Fellowship Day, May 1987 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1986-1988 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Savvy Award, April 1987 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - State Meeting, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Slides, 1986-1987 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Scrapbooks and Ephemera, 1966-1981
  This series contains items dating from 1966 to 1981, arranged chronologically. The three scrapbooks in this series have been disassembled for preservation purposes. The pages from each scrapbook have been removed from their covers and retained in their original order, while the covers have been placed in a separate box.
  - Scrapbook, 1966 (Ovs box 8, Item 1)
  - Scrapbooks, 1967, 1981 (Ovs box 9, Item 1)
  - Scrapbook Covers, 1966, 1967, 1981 (Ovs box 10, Item 1)
  - Newspaper Clipping, 1982 (Ovs box 10, Item 2)
  - Bandana, undated (Ovs box 10, Item 3)
  - Leather Binder, undated (Ovs box 10, Item 4)
  - Plastic 3-Ring Binder, undated (Ovs box 10, Item 5)